[A Splendid Match]
[Un partido espléndido]
[Episode 33]
[Episodio 33]
How could I possibly have
¿Cómo podría yo tener?
a useless nephew like you?
¿Un sobrino inútil como tú?
If you didn't have the ability,
Si no tenías la capacidad,
why did you take on this job?
¿Por qué aceptaste este trabajo?
It's lucky we found out early.
Menos mal que nos dimos cuenta a tiempo.
If these goods had reached the Nine Border Garrisons
Si estos bienes hubieran llegado a las Nueve Guarniciones Fronterizas
and the soldiers ended up freezing, that would've been bad enough—
y los soldados acabaron congelándose, eso ya habría sido bastante malo.
but if it shook the army's morale, that'd be the real problem.
Pero si eso afectara la moral del ejército, ese sí sería un verdadero problema.
And if the matter escalated,
Y si el asunto se agravaba,
and the Imperial Court traced it back to the Dai family—
y la Corte Imperial rastreó su origen hasta la familia Dai—
passing off inferior goods as proper ones,
hacer pasar productos de calidad inferior por productos de calidad,
embezzlement,
malversación,
pocketing court funds—
embolsarse fondos judiciales
that'd be the crime of deceiving the Emperor.
Eso sería el crimen de engañar al Emperador.
Do you all have a death wish?
¿Acaso todos ustedes desean morir?
Aunt.
Tía.
I...
I...
I know I was wrong.
Sé que me equivoqué.
From now on,
De aquí en adelante,
I swear I'll never do it again.
Te juro que nunca lo volveré a hacer.
Aunt,
Tía,
the most important thing now
Lo más importante ahora
is finding a way to cover it up.
está buscando la manera de encubrirlo.
Aunt,
Tía,
the Imperial Court's deadline
el plazo de la Corte Imperial
is only three days away.
Faltan solo tres días.
Scraping together 50,000
Reunir 50.000
winter coats,
abrigos de invierno,
I...
I...
I truly can't come up with that many.
Sinceramente, no se me ocurren tantos.
My good Aunt,
Mi buena tía,
please help me!
¡por favor, ayúdame!
Madam.
Señora.
My good Aunt.
Mi buena tía.
Madam Chen requests an audience.
La señora Chen solicita una audiencia.
Madam Chen?
¿Señora Chen?
I heard you've been troubled lately
He oído que has estado preocupado últimamente.
over the winter coats
sobre los abrigos de invierno
for the Nine Border Garrisons' soldiers.
para los soldados de las Nueve Guarniciones Fronterizas.
Please don't get me wrong.
Por favor, no me malinterpretes.
I didn't mean to pry.
No era mi intención entrometerme.
It's just that my grandmother's family
Es que la familia de mi abuela
once also bid
una vez también pujó
for this Ministry of War's order.
por esta orden del Ministerio de Guerra.
I heard that this batch of winter coats
He oído que este lote de abrigos de invierno
is still short in quantity.
Todavía escasea en cantidad.
If you don't mind,
Si no te importa,
I happen to have
Resulta que tengo
some stock on hand.
Tenemos algunas unidades disponibles.
How many do you have?
¿Cuántos tienes?
Qingpu.
Qingpu.
[Ji's Capital Region Winter Coats Ledger]
[Libro de abrigos de invierno de la región capital de Ji]
[Tongzhou Canal, North Bank Warehouse, Fine Cotton Padded Jackets, 10,000 pieces]
[Canal de Tongzhou, Almacén de la Ribera Norte, Chaquetas acolchadas de algodón fino, 10.000 unidades]
Across all the warehouses combined,
En todos los almacenes combinados,
we currently have 35,000 in total.
Actualmente tenemos un total de 35.000.
[Capital City, Chaoyang Gate South Warehouse, Silk-lined Cotton Robes, 5,000]
[Capital City, Almacén Sur de la Puerta Chaoyang , Batas de algodón forradas de seda, 5.000]
If that's still not enough,
Si eso todavía no es suficiente,
we can push our suppliers these days,
Hoy en día podemos presionar a nuestros proveedores,
and we may be able to get more.
y tal vez podamos conseguir más.
That's very thoughtful of you.
Eso es muy considerado de tu parte.
Then I won't stand on ceremony.
Entonces no me andaré con formalidades.
Let's just say the Dai family
Digamos que la familia Dai
is buying these coats from you.
te está comprando estos abrigos.
Name your price,
Diga su precio,
and we will pay in full.
y pagaremos la totalidad.
It's your call.
Tú decides.
You have truly
Realmente lo has hecho
saved me from a dire situation;
Me salvó de una situación desesperada;
I really need to thank you properly.
Realmente necesito agradecerte como es debido.
Madam.
Señora.
Please don't treat me like an outsider.
Por favor, no me trates como a un extraño.
Jiuheng sees the Senior Grand Secretary as his father,
Jiuheng ve al Gran Secretario Mayor como su padre,
and you as his mother.
y tú como su madre.
I feel exactly the same way.
Yo siento exactamente lo mismo.
This is
Esto es
the least we can do.
Es lo mínimo que podemos hacer.
I heard that recently,
Lo escuché recientemente,
you and Mrs. Wang
usted y la Sra. Wang
had a bit of a disagreement.
Tuvimos un pequeño desacuerdo.
She is just
Ella es simplemente
hot-tempered.
irascible.
Please don't take it personal.
Por favor, no te lo tomes como algo personal.
Yes.
Sí.
How about this?
¿Qué te parece esto?
Next month's tea gathering,
La reunión de té del próximo mes,
I'll have you host it.
Te pediré que lo organices.
What do you think?
¿Qué opinas?
Thank you, Madam.
Gracias, señora.
You couldn't even handle such a simple task.
Ni siquiera pudiste realizar una tarea tan sencilla.
Third Master,
Tercer Maestro,
I didn't expect the timing to be so unfortunate.
No esperaba que el momento fuera tan inoportuno.
Just as I was about to talk
Justo cuando estaba a punto de hablar
to Qingpu,
a Qingpu,
Second Master Yao from the Ji family
Segundo Maestro Yao de la familia Ji
suddenly showed up,
apareció de repente,
and he came specifically
y vino específicamente
for the winter clothes.
para la ropa de invierno.
I...
I...
Alright.
Está bien.
Go receive your punishment.
Ve a recibir tu castigo.
Yes.
Sí.
Third Master,
Tercer Maestro,
you clearly
claramente
did all of this for Madam's sake.
Hice todo esto por el bien de la señora.
Why not just tell her?
¿Por qué no decírselo?
Do you remember what I told you before?
¿Recuerdas lo que te dije antes?
She once
Ella una vez
wanted to do business in Shanxi
Quería hacer negocios en Shanxi.
as a backup plan for her future.
como plan B para su futuro.
After marrying me,
Después de casarse conmigo,
she stayed in the capital,
Ella se quedó en la capital,
yet she still takes the business of
Sin embargo, ella todavía se encarga del negocio de
Linxia Restaurant very seriously.
El restaurante Linxia se lo toma muy en serio.
If I interfere too much,
Si interfiero demasiado,
it will only make her uncomfortable.
Eso solo la incomodará.
I see.
Veo.
We didn't
No lo hicimos
help Madam directly this time,
esta vez, ayude directamente a la señora.
but
pero
bringing down Zheng Xiaoyou
derribando a Zheng Xiaoyou
still settles
aún se asienta
the score for her.
la puntuación para ella.
That's true.
Eso es cierto.
I don't care!
¡No me importa!
Gu Jinzhao has gone too far.
Gu Jinzhao ha ido demasiado lejos.
You have to get revenge for me!
¡Tienes que vengarte por mí!
How am I supposed to do that?
¿Cómo se supone que voy a hacer eso?
You were running a usury business outside,
Usted dirigía un negocio de usura en el exterior,
which was a serious matter,
lo cual era un asunto serio,
yet you never told me.
Pero nunca me lo dijiste.
Now that you've suffered losses,
Ahora que has sufrido pérdidas,
and you come crying to me?
¿Y vienes llorando a mí?
You even bypassed me
Incluso me pasaste por alto.
and dealt with Zheng Xiaoyou directly.
y trató directamente con Zheng Xiaoyou.
He's the Governor of Shuntian Prefecture,
Él es el gobernador de la prefectura de Shuntian,
not your doorman.
No es tu portero.
How many times have you
¿Cuántas veces has...?
covered for Zheng Xiaoyou?
¿Cubierto para Zheng Xiaoyou?
What's wrong with me giving him a few orders?
¿Qué tiene de malo que le dé algunas órdenes?
Madam, here's a message from Chen Mansion.
Señora, le envío un mensaje desde la Mansión Chen.
The Chen Mansion again?
¿Otra vez la mansión Chen?
[Linxia Restaurant Invitation]
[Invitación al restaurante Linxia]
A tea gathering...
Una reunión para tomar el té...
It's a tea gathering.
Es una reunión para tomar el té.
[Inviting Madam to Linxia Restaurant on the 6th day of Midsummer]
[Invitando a la señora al restaurante Linxia el sexto día del solsticio de verano]
What is it?
¿Qué es?
Linxia Restaurant.
Restaurante Linxi.
Madam Fu actually
La señora Fu en realidad
let Gu Jinzhao host the tea gathering!
¡Que Gu Jinzhao sea el anfitrión de la reunión del té!
This Gu family's daughter
Esta es la hija de la familia Gu.
is really something.
Es algo realmente especial.
It seems she has won
Parece que ella ha ganado
the favor of the Grand Secretary's wife.
el favor de la esposa del Gran Secretario.
Don't.
No.
No, no, no.
No, no, no.
-So infuriating! -Those are expensive!
¡Qué rabia! ¡Son carísimos!
This...
Este...
These are...
Estos son...
Not that one!
¡Ese no!
-I'm so mad! -You can't throw that one!
-¡Estoy furioso! -¡No puedes lanzar esa!
Don't throw this!
¡No tires esto!
That one is very expensive!
¡Ese es muy caro!
Don't.
No.
Don't be mad.
No te enfades.
Calm down.
Cálmate.
It's not a big deal.
No es gran cosa.
I'll find a way to get back at her.
Encontraré la manera de vengarme de ella.
Just listen to me.
Solo escúchame.
I've already asked Zheng Xiaoyou
Ya le pregunté a Zheng Xiaoyou.
to gather evidence of Third Mr. Chen's crimes.
para reunir pruebas de los crímenes del tercer señor Chen.
Really?
¿En realidad?
Once we have solid evidence,
Una vez que tengamos pruebas sólidas,
I'll have him formally impeached.
Haré que se le inicie un proceso de destitución formal.
How does that sound?
¿Qué te parece?
Master. Master.
Maestro. Maestro.
Something terrible has happened!
¡Ha ocurrido algo terrible!
What is it now?
¿Qué es ahora?
A message has just arrived.
Acaba de llegar un mensaje.
Lord Zheng Xiaoyou was in the middle of
El señor Zheng Xiaoyou estaba en medio de
holding court at Shuntian Prefecture
Celebrando audiencia en la prefectura de Shuntian
when the Court of Judicial Review burst in
cuando el Tribunal de Revisión Judicial irrumpió en
and dragged him away on the spot.
y se lo llevaron a rastras en el acto.
They say he's facing multiple charges:
Dicen que se enfrenta a múltiples cargos:
taking bribes, selling official posts,
aceptar sobornos, vender cargos oficiales,
and allowing his servants to commit acts of violence.
y permitiendo que sus sirvientes cometieran actos de violencia.
Third Mr. Chen
Tercer señor Chen
It must be Third Mr. Chen.
Debe ser el tercer señor Chen.
Third Mr. Chen.
Tercer señor Chen.
Third Mr. Chen!
¡Tercer señor Chen!
You are so skillful, Madam.
Usted es muy hábil, señora.
With just a few adjustments,
Con tan solo unos pocos ajustes,
this looks incredibly elegant.
Esto tiene un aspecto increíblemente elegante.
It's just a way
Es solo una forma
to pass the time.
para pasar el tiempo.
It's not as amazing as you make it sound.
No es tan increíble como lo pintas.
I heard
Escuché
that Jiuheng's wife
esa esposa de Jiuheng
and Wang Xuanfan's wife
y la esposa de Wang Xuanfan
have been fighting
han estado luchando
quite fiercely lately.
bastante enérgicamente últimamente.
Oh, absolutely.
Oh, absolutamente.
They even brought their drama right in front of me.
Incluso montaron su drama justo delante de mí.
Like husband, like wife.
De tal palo, tal astilla.
Usually,
Generalmente,
Jiuheng
Jiuheng
and Wang Xuanfan
y Wang Xuanfan
are competing with each other as well.
También están compitiendo entre sí.
Wasn't that because
¿No fue eso porque...?
my husband deliberately used some tricks
Mi esposo usó deliberadamente algunos trucos.
to put them against each other?
¿Para enfrentarlos entre sí?
Madam,
Señora,
you are just as capable as Master.
Eres tan capaz como el Maestro.
What brings you here?
¿Qué te trae por aquí?
I heard Zheng Xiaoyou was arrested.
He oído que Zheng Xiaoyou fue arrestado.
Was that your doing?
¿Eso fue obra tuya?
You could say that.
Se podría decir eso.
Thank you.
Gracias.
There's no need to thank me.
No hace falta que me des las gracias.
Zheng Xiaoyou
Zheng Xiaoyou
was notorious during his time as Governor of Shuntian Prefecture.
Fue tristemente célebre durante su mandato como gobernador de la prefectura de Shuntian.
Previously, out of respect
Anteriormente, por respeto
for Wang Xuanfan,
para Wang Xuanfan,
I didn't touch him.
No lo toqué.
But he actually
Pero él en realidad
had the nerve to cross you.
Tuvo el descaro de enfrentarse a ti.
If I let him off again,
Si lo dejo escapar otra vez,
I don't deserve to be your husband.
No merezco ser tu marido.
Hearing you speak just now
Te escuché hablar hace un momento
suddenly reminded me
de repente me lo recordó
of the first time
de la primera vez
I met you at the Ji Mansion.
Te conocí en la mansión Ji.
What was I like back then?
¿Cómo era yo entonces?
Decisive, powerful, and commanding.
Decisivo, poderoso e imponente.
Well, now
Ahora bien
you've married
te has casado
to that powerful and commanding husband.
a ese marido poderoso y autoritario.
In the future,
En el futuro,
whenever you run into trouble,
cada vez que tengas problemas,
you don't have to
no tienes que hacerlo
carry everything on your own anymore.
Ya no tienes que cargar con todo tú solo.
Even now,
Aún ahora,
you're already carrying things for me.
Ya me estás llevando cosas.
If it weren't for you,
Si no fuera por ti,
how could I be so calm?
¿Cómo pude estar tan tranquilo?
Madam Wang could crush
La señora Wang podría aplastar
a merchant like me
un comerciante como yo
without lifting her finger.
sin mover un dedo.
Actually,
De hecho,
ever since the first time
desde la primera vez
I met you,
Te conocí,
I've been relying on you.
He estado contando contigo.
Our Ji family,
Nuestra familia Ji,
and the Gu family...
y la familia Gu...
Think about how much you've helped me,
Piensa en cuánto me has ayudado,
and how many times you've saved me.
y cuántas veces me has salvado.
Honestly, I'm worried
Sinceramente, estoy preocupado.
that one day,
que un día,
I'll get so used to relying on you.
Me acostumbraré tanto a depender de ti.
You certainly know
Sin duda lo sabes
how to sweet-talk people.
Cómo engatusar a la gente.
If you keep this up,
Si sigues así,
I might actually believe you.
Puede que te crea.
I am a merchant's daughter.
Soy hija de un comerciante.
Sweet-talking is my specialty.
Engatusar es mi especialidad.
Is that so?
¿Es eso así?
My Lady.
Mi señora.
[Immersed in the Classics and History]
[Inmersos en los clásicos y la historia]
What is it?
¿Qué es?
Young Master Xuanqing
Joven Maestro Xuanqing
is waiting outside the door.
está esperando fuera de la puerta.
He wants to know what time you plan
Quiere saber a qué hora planeas
to leave for the Yu Mansion tomorrow.
Mañana partiré hacia la Mansión Yu.
Tell him we'll leave
Dile que nos vamos
between 7 and 9 in the morning.
entre las 7 y las 9 de la mañana.
Yes.
Sí.
Are you free tomorrow?
¿Estás libre mañana?
What's wrong?
¿Qué ocurre?
How about we go together
¿Qué tal si vamos juntos?
to the Yu Mansion to set the date?
¿A la mansión Yu para fijar la fecha?
Okay.
Bueno.
[Diligent by Day, Vigilant by Night]
[Diligente de día, vigilante de noche]
Uncle.
Tío.
Aunt.
Tía.
Please get up, nephew.
Levántate, sobrino.
Have a seat.
Toma asiento.
Our Old Madam
Nuestra anciana señora
had a master pick three auspicious dates.
Un maestro escogió tres fechas propicias.
Please take a look, Master Yu
Por favor, eche un vistazo, Maestro Yu
and Madam Yu.
y la señora Yu.
Thank you.
Gracias.
[November 8th, March 8th, December 6th of the lunar calendar]
[8 de noviembre, 8 de marzo, 6 de diciembre del calendario lunar]
Not bad.
Nada mal.
These three dates,
Estas tres fechas,
all look great to me.
Todos me parecen estupendos.
We'll leave the final choice to you and Lord Chen.
Dejaremos la decisión final en manos de usted y del señor Chen.
Then let Wanxue choose a date.
Entonces, deja que Wanxue elija una fecha.
Yes.
Sí.
I don't know what's been
No sé qué ha pasado
bothering Wanxue lately.
últimamente Wanxue está molestando.
She's so deeply distressed
Está profundamente angustiada.
that she can barely sleep at night.
que apenas puede dormir por la noche.
How about
¿Qué tal si...?
I go check on her?
¿Voy a ver cómo está?
Well...
Bien...
I happen to want to
Resulta que quiero
have a word with her alone.
Habla con ella a solas.
Alright.
Está bien.
That's good.
Eso es bueno.
Please escort
Por favor, acompañen
Madam Chen over.
La señora Chen ha terminado.
Yes.
Sí.
I'll head over now.
Voy para allá ahora.
Alright.
Está bien.
Go ahead.
Adelante.
Uncle, Aunt.
Tío, tía.
I prepared a gift for Wanxue,
Preparé un regalo para Wanxue,
but I left it in the carriage outside.
pero lo dejé en el vagón de afuera.
I'll go get it now.
Iré a buscarlo ahora.
Alright. Go ahead.
De acuerdo. Adelante.
Third Aunt.
Tercera tía.
You should be in the front courtyard.
Debes estar en el patio delantero.
What are you doing out here?
¿Qué haces aquí fuera?
There are a few things
Hay algunas cosas
I'd like you to pass along to Wanxue.
Me gustaría que se lo transmitieras a Wanxue.
Excuse us, you two.
Discúlpennos, ustedes dos.
Please step away for a moment.
Por favor, aléjese un momento.
It really isn't easy
Realmente no es fácil
to get a chance to talk to you.
para tener la oportunidad de hablar contigo.
The way you've been avoiding me lately
La forma en que me has estado evitando últimamente
has made me suspect something.
me ha hecho sospechar algo.
What is it?
¿Qué es?
I suspect you still can't
Sospecho que aún no puedes.
let go of what happened between us.
Deja atrás lo que pasó entre nosotros.
Shut up.
Callarse la boca.
You misunderstood.
Lo has entendido mal.
Misunderstood?
¿Incomprendido?
Yes.
Sí.
Three years ago,
Hace tres años,
you asked me to meet at Yong'an Bridge.
Me pediste que nos viéramos en el puente de Yong'an.
I went there.
Yo fui allí.
I really did.
De verdad que sí.
I even saw the kite
Incluso vi la cometa.
you flew for me.
Volaste por mí.
The reason I didn't come to see you
La razón por la que no vine a verte
was because Third Uncle...
fue porque el tercer tío...
I don't want to hear this.
No quiero oír esto.
It was supposed to be us
Se suponía que íbamos a ser nosotros
being together.
estar juntos.
The servants can't hear us right now.
Los sirvientes no pueden oírnos ahora mismo.
But if you keep looking back
Pero si sigues mirando hacia atrás
at them like that,
mirándolos así,
they'll start to suspect something.
Empezarán a sospechar algo.
I don't know
No sé
why you're telling me this.
¿Por qué me estás contando esto?
If you're trying to test my attitude,
Si estás tratando de poner a prueba mi actitud,
then let me make myself clear:
Permítanme entonces aclararme:
What's past
¿Qué es el pasado?
is in the past.
es cosa del pasado.
It's water under the bridge,
Eso ya es agua pasada,
and I forgot about that long ago.
Y lo olvidé hace mucho tiempo.
Forgot?
¿Olvidó?
Water under the bridge?
¿Agua pasada no mota?
That's right.
Así es.
Since you've made your choice,
Ya que has tomado tu decisión,
please keep it firmly in mind
Por favor, téngalo muy presente
and stop causing trouble for no reason.
y deja de causar problemas sin motivo.
You came to the Yu Mansion today
Hoy has venido a la Mansión Yu
to set the wedding date.
para fijar la fecha de la boda.
Wanxue is a good girl
Wanxue es una buena chica.
and she loves you wholeheartedly.
y ella te ama con todo su corazón.
Even after
Incluso después
the things you said to her that day,
las cosas que le dijiste ese día,
she still wants to be with you.
Ella todavía quiere estar contigo.
Don't take what you have for granted.
No des por sentado lo que tienes.
Don't break her heart again.
No le rompas el corazón otra vez.
Third...
Tercero...
Do you have any idea what you're saying?
¿Tienes idea de lo que estás diciendo?
For the sake of the Yu family,
Por el bien de la familia Yu,
I will leave you some dignity.
Te dejaré algo de dignidad.
From today on,
Desde este día,
you'll move into the Hanlin Academy.
Te mudarás a la Academia Hanlin.
Without my permission,
Sin mi permiso,
you can't return to the mansion.
No puedes regresar a la mansión.
Young Master.
El señorito.
Are you alright?
¿Estás bien?
[Thrice Reflections Against Greed; Ninefold Virtues in the Sound of the Qin]
[Tres reflexiones contra la codicia; nueve virtudes en el sonido del Qin]
It seems they first met
Parece que se conocieron por primera vez.
[Immersed in the Classics and History]
[Inmersos en los clásicos y la historia]
at the coming-of-age ceremony.
en la ceremonia de mayoría de edad.
That day, Madam accidentally fell into the water.
Ese día, la señora cayó accidentalmente al agua.
After waking up,
Después de despertar,
she mistakenly believed
Ella creyó erróneamente
that Young Master Xuanqing was the one who saved her.
Que el joven maestro Xuanqing fue quien la salvó.
So she prepared generous gifts
Así que preparó generosos regalos.
for Young Master Xuanqing.
Para el joven maestro Xuanqing.
Later, Madam came to the capital.
Más tarde, la señora llegó a la capital.
And Ji Yao, the Second Young Master Ji,
Y Ji Yao, el segundo joven maestro Ji,
was studying at Cunshan Academy,
estaba estudiando en la Academia Cunshan,
when Madam brought him to the academy,
Cuando la señora lo trajo a la academia,
she met Young Master Xuanqing again.
Se reencontró con el joven maestro Xuanqing.
Once,
Una vez,
Young Lord Ye had
Joven Señor Ye tenía
a confrontation with Madam at the academy.
un enfrentamiento con la señora en la academia.
I've asked around
He preguntado por ahí
and learned that Madam
y supe que la señora
had actually gone there that day
De hecho, había ido allí ese día.
to return a book to Young Master Xuanqing.
devolver un libro al joven maestro Xuanqing.
After that,
Después,
they had some interactions.
Tuvieron algunas interacciones.
Until Young Master Xuanqing's birthday that year,
Hasta el cumpleaños del joven maestro Xuanqing ese año,
Madam...
Señora...
Go on.
Seguir.
Yes.
Sí.
Madam made a kite herself.
La señora hizo una cometa ella misma.
They agreed
Ellos estuvieron de acuerdo
to meet at Yong'an Bridge.
Nos encontraremos en el puente de Yong'an.
But for some reason,
Pero por alguna razón,
Young Master Xuanqing never showed up.
El joven maestro Xuanqing nunca apareció.
And after that,
Y después de eso,
things simply faded away.
Las cosas simplemente se desvanecieron.
I have
Tengo
another presumptuous request.
Otra petición presuntuosa.
Could you
Podrías
hold off on
posponer
arranging the marriage for me until after
organizando el matrimonio para mí hasta después
the metropolitan examination is over?
¿Terminó el examen metropolitano?
Why?
¿Por qué?
Do you have
Tiene
any other thoughts?
¿Alguna otra idea?
No.
No.
I just
Yo solo
don't want to rush it.
No quiero apresurarlo.
I was the one who arranged
Yo fui quien lo organizó
his marriage with the Yu family.
su matrimonio con la familia Yu.
He was somewhat reluctant at the time.
En aquel momento se mostró algo reacio.
It wasn't until I told him the truth about
No fue hasta que le conté la verdad sobre
his birth father's death that he agreed.
La muerte de su padre biológico, a lo que él accedió.
So it seems
Eso parece
he chose his future
Él eligió su futuro
over Jinzhao.
sobre Jinzhao.
Third Master.
Tercer Maestro.
Madam was young at the time,
La señora era joven en aquel entonces,
falling in love for the first time.
enamorarse por primera vez.
It was only natural for her to be a little naive.
Era natural que fuera un poco ingenua.
Falling in love for the first time.
Enamorarse por primera vez.
Falling in love for the first time...
Enamorarse por primera vez...
Have someone to keep an eye on him.
Que alguien lo vigile.
You mean him...
¿Te refieres a él...?
or her?
¿O ella?
Chen Xuanqing.
Chen Xuan Qing.
Yes.
Sí.
Madam was young at the time,
La señora era joven en aquel entonces,
falling in love for the first time.
enamorarse por primera vez.
It was only natural for her to be a little naive.
Era natural que fuera un poco ingenua.
I plan to remain unmarried in the future.
Planeo permanecer soltera en el futuro.
Sages all say that
Todos los sabios dicen que
the key to marriage
La clave del matrimonio
lies in mutual suitability.
reside en la compatibilidad mutua.
This means that marriage
Esto significa que el matrimonio
should be good for both parties.
Debería ser beneficioso para ambas partes.
That's the principle.
Ese es el principio.
What's past
¿Qué es el pasado?
is in the past.
es cosa del pasado.
It's water under the bridge.
Eso ya es agua pasada.
And I forgot about that long ago.
Y lo olvidé hace mucho tiempo.
Water under the bridge?
¿Agua pasada no mota?
That's right.
Así es.
Since you've made your choice,
Ya que has tomado tu decisión,
please keep it firmly in mind,
Por favor, téngalo muy presente.
and stop causing trouble for no reason.
y deja de causar problemas sin motivo.
I know perfectly well
Lo sé perfectamente bien
that whether it's my anger toward Jinzhao
que si es mi ira hacia Jinzhao
or my hatred toward Chen Xuanqing,
o mi odio hacia Chen Xuanqing,
it's all meaningless—
Todo carece de sentido.
childish, even.
infantil, incluso.
But I...
Pero yo...
still can't get over it.
Todavía no puedo superarlo.
Moving back to the Hanlin Academy might be for the best.
Quizás lo mejor sea volver a la Academia Hanlin .
Being away from the mansion
Estar lejos de la mansión
will let you focus on your duties.
te permitirá concentrarte en tus deberes.
After some time,
Después de algún tiempo,
you can go back and apologize to Third Master.
Puedes volver y disculparte con el Tercer Maestro.
There's still a chance to mend things.
Todavía hay una oportunidad de arreglar las cosas.
Apologize?
¿Disculparse?
What did I do wrong?
¿Qué hice mal?
Young Master.
El señorito.
All these years,
Todos estos años,
I've worked myself to the bone studying
Me he esforzado al máximo estudiando
just to bring honor to the Chen family.
Simplemente para honrar a la familia Chen.
I've catered to everyone in the Chen family.
He atendido a todos los miembros de la familia Chen.
Haven't I done enough?
¿No he hecho ya suficiente?
Just because the Chen family did me a favor,
Solo porque la familia Chen me hizo un favor,
and I have to compromise forever?
¿Y tengo que ceder para siempre?
Because he took me in,
Porque me acogió,
I have to do
Tengo que hacerlo
whatever he says?
¿Lo que él diga?
I'm not allowed to disobey him at all,
No tengo permitido desobedecerle en absoluto.
is that right?
¿Es correcto?
Even when the woman I love
Incluso cuando la mujer que amo
was taken away from me,
me fue arrebatado,
I'm not even allowed
Ni siquiera me lo permiten.
to show the slightest bit of sadness.
mostrar el más mínimo rastro de tristeza.
Young Master,
El señorito,
keep your voice down.
Baja la voz.
This is the duty room.
Esta es la sala de guardia.
What are you afraid of?
¿A qué le tienes miedo?
Do you think Chen Yanyun
¿Crees que Chen Yanyun...?
will still help us?
¿Aún nos ayudará?
You're wrong.
Te equivocas.
He is
Él es
narrow-minded
de mente estrecha
and vindictive.
y vengativo.
Now that he knows
Ahora que lo sabe
Gu Jinzhao once had feelings for me,
Gu Jinzhao una vez sintió algo por mí,
so he wants
así que él quiere
to see me dead.
para verme muerto.
That won't happen, Young Master.
Eso no sucederá, joven amo.
You are still the Tanhua, after all.
Después de todo, sigues siendo el Tanhua.
There will always be opportunities.
Siempre habrá oportunidades.
What opportunities?
¿Qué oportunidades?
Others just think
Otros simplemente piensan
that I have a Grand Secretary uncle—
que tengo un tío Gran Secretario—
a powerful tree to rely on.
Un árbol poderoso en el que confiar.
What they don't see
Lo que no ven
is that he never gives me a chance;
es que nunca me da una oportunidad;
on the contrary, he's on guard against me.
Al contrario, está en guardia contra mí.
He refuses to support me,
Él se niega a apoyarme,
yet still occupies the moral high ground,
Sin embargo, sigue ocupando la posición moral superior,
making it impossible for me to seek another patron
lo que me imposibilita buscar otro patrocinador.
without looking ungrateful.
sin parecer desagradecido.
I hate it.
Lo odio.
Yunting,
Yunting,
do you know?
¿Sabes?
I hate all of it!
¡Lo odio todo!
Young Master.
El señorito.
Please stop saying such things.
Por favor, deja de decir esas cosas.
I beg you.
Te lo ruego.
Please keep these words to yourself.
Por favor, guárdate estas palabras para ti.
Please don't say it anymore.
Por favor, no lo digas más.
Don't say another word.
No digas ni una palabra más.
What?
¿Qué?
You're saying Chen Xuanqing
Estás diciendo Chen Xuanqing
moved into the Hanlin Academy?
¿Se mudó a la Academia Hanlin?
He left last night.
Se marchó anoche.
They say there's a new assignment at the Hanlin Academy,
Dicen que hay una nueva asignación en la Academia Hanlin,
so he returned there to work.
Así que regresó allí a trabajar.
My Lady.
Mi señora.
Now you can finally relax a bit.
Ahora por fin puedes relajarte un poco.
I just feel that
Simplemente siento que
Third Master noticed something.
El tercer maestro notó algo.
You mean
Te refieres a
Chen Xuanqing left
Chen Xuanqing se fue
because of Third Master?
¿Por culpa del Tercer Maestro?
I'm not sure.
No estoy seguro.
But these past few days,
Pero estos últimos días,
Third Master has been much quieter.
Third Master ha estado mucho más tranquilo.
How about I go ask Chen Yi?
¿Qué tal si voy a preguntarle a Chen Yi?
How?
¿Cómo?
Fair enough.
Me parece bien.
There's no good way to ask something like that.
No hay una buena manera de preguntar algo así.
It's all Chen Xuanqing's fault.
Todo es culpa de Chen Xuanqing.
Everything was already in the past,
Todo ya era cosa del pasado,
yet he insisted on stirring it up again.
Sin embargo, insistió en volver a avivar la polémica.
Forget it.
Olvídalo.
I haven't done anything
No he hecho nada
shameful anyway.
Vergonzoso de todos modos.
If it weren't for Wanxue,
Si no fuera por Wanxue,
there'd be nothing for me
no habría nada para mí
to hide in the first place.
para esconderse en primer lugar.
I might as well
Podría hacerlo bien
just tell him directly.
Díselo directamente.
What are you going to say?
¿Qué vas a decir?
There's something I should tell you.
Hay algo que debo decirte.
I used to
Yo solía
have feelings
tener sentimientos
for Chen Xuanqing.
Para Chen Xuanqing.
No. That won't do.
No. Eso no servirá.
Let me try again.
Déjame intentarlo de nuevo.
When I was young and naive,
Cuando era joven e ingenuo,
I had some
Tuve algunos
feelings for
sentimientos por
Chen Xuanqing.
Chen Xuan Qing.
That sounds even worse somehow.
Eso suena aún peor de alguna manera.
Never mind.
No importa.
I haven't done anything wrong.
No he hecho nada malo.
What do I have to be afraid of?
¿De qué tengo que tener miedo?
Exactly.
Exactamente.
Madam.
Señora.
Where is Third Master?
¿Dónde está el Tercer Maestro?
Third Master said
El tercer maestro dijo:
he'll be staying at the Hall of Literary Profundity tonight,
Esta noche se alojará en el Salón de la Profundidad Literaria.
and won't return to the mansion.
y no volverá a la mansión.
I see.
Veo.
My Lady.
Mi señora.
Third Master is avoiding you.
El Tercer Maestro te está evitando.
That's not like him at all.
Eso no es propio de él en absoluto.
He has never
Él nunca ha
avoided anyone like this before.
Antes había evitado a personas así.
I'll go pack some clothes.
Voy a empacar algo de ropa.
Have Chen Yi take them
Que Chen Yi los tome
to the Hall of Literary Profundity.
al Salón de la Profundidad Literaria.
Maybe he really is just busy.
Quizás simplemente está ocupado.
[Hall of Literary Profundity]
[Salón de la Profundidad Literaria]
Jiuheng, you haven't left yet?
Jiuheng, ¿aún no te has ido?
[Perfect Harmony]
[Armonía perfecta]
I have to say,
Tengo que decir,
have you lost weight?
¿Has perdido peso?
Your complexion doesn't look good either.
Tu cutis tampoco tiene buen aspecto.
Have you been too tired lately?
¿Has estado muy cansado últimamente?
Yeah.
Sí.
[Virtue Equal to Heaven and Earth]
[Virtud igual al cielo y a la tierra]
The land reform, maritime trade, and river maintenance,
La reforma agraria, el comercio marítimo y el mantenimiento de los ríos,
have all piled up at once.
se han acumulado todos a la vez.
The memorials never stop coming.
Los homenajes nunca cesan.
[Virtue Equal to Heaven and Earth]
[Virtud igual al cielo y a la tierra]
While the Senior Grand Secretary is away,
Mientras el Gran Secretario Mayor está ausente,
you should head home early tonight.
Deberías volver a casa temprano esta noche.
I've been married for years,
Llevo años casada,
[Virtue Equal to Heaven and Earth]
[Virtud igual al cielo y a la tierra]
but you're still newlywed.
pero aún sois recién casados.
By the way,
Por cierto,
the Reader-in-Waiting of the Hanlin Academy,
el Lector en Espera de la Academia Hanlin,
Shao Heng, has left office for the mourning period.
Shao Heng ha dejado su cargo por el período de luto.
The post of Imperial Tutor is now vacant.
El puesto de Tutor Imperial se encuentra vacante.
Do you want
Quieres
to appoint Xuanqing to the position?
¿Nombrar a Xuanqing para el puesto?
Thank you for your kindness, Zhonglu.
Gracias por tu amabilidad, Zhonglu.
But...
Pero...
Xuanqing has been in the Hanlin Academy
Xuanqing ha estado en la Academia Hanlin.
for less than two years.
durante menos de dos años.
He's too inexperienced.
Es demasiado inexperto.
If he gets promoted now,
Si lo ascienden ahora,
it'll draw the wrong kind of attention.
Eso atraerá la atención equivocada.
Let's forget about it.
Olvidémonos de eso.
You are always so cautious.
Siempre eres tan precavido.
Alright, get back to work.
Muy bien, volvamos al trabajo.
[Perfect Harmony]
[Armonía perfecta]
I'm heading home now.
Me voy a casa ahora.
Someone.
Alguien.
Prime Minister.
Primer ministro.
Go fetch some wine for me.
Ve a buscarme un poco de vino.
Yes.
Sí.
[Ji family's Silk Store]
[Tienda de seda de la familia Ji]
Madam.
Señora.
Third Master won't be coming back today.
El Tercer Maestro no regresará hoy.
My Lady.
Mi señora.
It's already been three days.
Ya han pasado tres días.
I can't keep enduring this.
No puedo seguir soportando esto.
If this drags on any longer,
Si esto se prolonga más,
even if he can stand it,
incluso si puede soportarlo,
I won't be able to take it.
No podré soportarlo.
Madam?
¿Señora?
Will Master be staying
¿Se quedará el Maestro?
at the Hall of Literary Profundity again tonight?
¿De nuevo esta noche en el Salón de la Profundidad Literaria ?
Yes.
Sí.
What about tomorrow?
¿Y mañana?
Tomorrow as well?
¿Mañana también?
Most likely.
Lo más probable.
You must be able
Debes ser capaz
to send things into the palace.
enviar cosas al palacio.
Help me send a message to Master.
Ayúdame a enviar un mensaje al Maestro.
Tell him I want to see him.
Dile que quiero verlo.
If he refuses to leave the palace,
Si se niega a abandonar el palacio,
then tell him
Entonces díselo
I'll wait for him outside Xihua Gate.
Lo esperaré fuera de la Puerta de Xihua.
If he's got the nerve,
Si tiene el descaro,
he better never come back.
Más le vale no volver jamás.
Well...
Bien...
Madam.
Señora.
Third Master isn't
El Tercer Maestro no lo es
at the Hall of Literary Profundity today.
En el Salón de la Profundidad Literaria hoy.
He's meeting guests at Baoxiang Temple.
Está recibiendo a unos invitados en el templo de Baoxiang.
Thank you.
Gracias.
[Baoxiang Temple]
Templo Baoxiang
This is a restricted area. Leave now!
Esta es una zona restringida. ¡Abandónela ahora!
I'm here to see Chen Yanyun.
Estoy aquí para ver a Chen Yanyun.
I'm his wife.
Soy su esposa.
His Lordship has ordered
Su Señoría ha ordenado
that no one is allowed to disturb him.
que nadie tiene permitido molestarlo.
[Baoxiang Temple]
Templo Baoxiang
Who would have thought
¿Quién lo hubiera pensado?
Wang Xuanfan had already been colluding
Wang Xuanfan ya había estado conspirando
with Prince Chengqing back when he was
con el príncipe Chengqing cuando él era
a mere physician at the Provincial Administration Commission?
¿Un simple médico en la Comisión de Administración Provincial?
No wonder the Capital Garrison
No es de extrañar que la guarnición de la capital
kept losing over the past few months.
He estado perdiendo durante los últimos meses.
By the way, Jiuheng.
Por cierto, Jiuheng.
I did exactly as you instructed.
Hice exactamente lo que me indicaste.
I had Zhang Hengyi from the Ministry of Rites
Tuve a Zhang Hengyi del Ministerio de Ritos
submit an impeachment memorial.
presentar una moción de destitución.
If things go quickly,
Si las cosas van rápido,
His Majesty and the Senior Grand Secretary
Su Majestad y el Gran Secretario Principal
should see it tonight.
Debería verla esta noche.
I appreciate the help, Yao.
Agradezco tu ayuda, Yao.
No need to thank me.
No hace falta que me des las gracias.
Wang Xuanfan and I were friends for years,
Wang Xuanfan y yo fuimos amigos durante años,
but the moment you married Miss Gu,
pero en el momento en que te casaste con la señorita Gu,
he started putting up walls against us.
Empezó a ponernos muros.
However,
Sin embargo,
Wang Xuanfan wasn't wrong about that.
Wang Xuanfan no se equivocaba en eso.
Since we are now in-laws,
Ya que ahora somos familia política,
we should be much closer.
Deberíamos estar mucho más unidos.
Cheers, Yao.
Saludos, Yao.
Okay.
Bueno.
[Baoxiang Temple]
Templo Baoxiang
It really is much colder
Realmente hace mucho más frío.
in the mountains than in the city.
en las montañas que en la ciudad.
Earlier, I was even thinking
Antes incluso estaba pensando
about asking my fourth daughter-in-law
sobre preguntarle a mi cuarta nuera
and her mother
y su madre
to visit your mansion,
para visitar su mansión,
just to use it as a convenient cover.
simplemente para usarlo como una cubierta práctica.
After all, our interactions
Después de todo, nuestras interacciones
have always made certain people uneasy.
Siempre han incomodado a ciertas personas.
But I didn't expect
Pero no lo esperaba
you haven't even been staying
Ni siquiera te has estado quedando
at your own mansion lately.
últimamente en tu propia mansión.
There are so many things
Hay tantas cosas
to handle, big and small,
para manejar, grandes y pequeños,
so I chose to stay
Así que decidí quedarme
at the Hall of Literary Profundity.
en el Salón de la Profundidad Literaria.
I understand.
Entiendo.
Going home too late
Llegar a casa demasiado tarde
might get you a scolding.
Podrías ganarte una reprimenda.
Now that we are exposing Wang Xuanfan's
Ahora que estamos exponiendo a Wang Xuanfan
collusion with the late Prince Chengqing,
connivencia con el difunto príncipe Chengqing,
he will surely drag Gu Deyuan
Seguramente arrastrará a Gu Deyuan
down with him
abajo con él
to protect himself,
para protegerse,
hoping to implicate you as well.
con la esperanza de implicarte también.
Forgive me for nagging,
Perdóname por insistir,
but let me ask you one more time:
Pero permítame preguntarle una vez más:
Are we truly not going to
¿De verdad no vamos a...?
save Gu Deyuan?
¿Salvar a Gu Deyuan?
Gu Deyuan
Gu De Yuan
is an imperial censor,
es un censor imperial,
yet he is utterly corrupt
Sin embargo, es completamente corrupto.
and insatiably greedy.
y una codicia insaciable.
Even if Wang Xuanfan weren't investigating him,
Aunque Wang Xuanfan no lo estuviera investigando,
I would still punish him myself.
Yo mismo seguiría castigándolo.
Alright.
Está bien.
I will follow your lead and
Seguiré tu ejemplo y
place righteousness above family for once.
Pon la rectitud por encima de la familia por una vez.
Third Master, a messenger from the palace has arrived,
Tercer Maestro, ha llegado un mensajero del palacio.
saying His Majesty has summoned you urgently.
diciendo que Su Majestad le ha convocado con urgencia.
His Majesty must have seen the memorial.
Su Majestad debió haber visto el monumento.
Jiuheng, go to the palace quickly.
Jiuheng, ve rápido al palacio.
My Lady.
Mi señora.
The guards over there said
Los guardias de allí dijeron
that Third Master has headed down the mountain.
El Tercer Maestro ha bajado de la montaña.
Is he that afraid to see me?
¿Tiene tanto miedo de verme?
Forget it.
Olvídalo.
Let's go back too.
Volvamos también.
My Lady.
Mi señora.
I,
I,
Zhang Hengyi, Supervising Secretary of the Rites,
Zhang Hengyi, Secretario Supervisor de los Ritos,
have a memorial to present.
tener un monumento conmemorativo para presentar.
In October of the 25th year of Jingning,
En octubre del año 25 de Jingning,
Prince Chengqing plotted a rebellion.
El príncipe Chengqing planeó una rebelión.
In the first three months,
En los primeros tres meses,
our forces suffered constant defeats,
Nuestras fuerzas sufrieron constantes derrotas,
leading many to suspect that
lo que lleva a muchos a sospechar que
a mole in the court was leaking secrets.
Un topo en el tribunal estaba filtrando secretos.
And Wang Xuanfan,
Y Wang Xuanfan,
who was a physician at the Provincial Administration Commission,
quien era médico en la Comisión de Administración Provincial,
was on good terms with Prince Chengqing.
Mantenía una buena relación con el príncipe Chengqing.
Nonsense!
¡Disparates!
Your Majesty,
Su Majestad,
at that time, I had
En ese momento, yo tenía
no dealings with Prince Chengqing.
No tengo ningún trato con el príncipe Chengqing.
This Zhang Hengyi is
Este Zhang Hengyi es
fabricating allegations out of thin air!
¡Inventando acusaciones de la nada!
He harbors malicious intent
Alberga intenciones maliciosas
and deserves to be executed!
¡Y merece ser ejecutado!
Lord Zhang is not making things up out of thin air.
Lord Zhang no se está inventando nada .
Chen Jiuheng.
Chen Jiu Heng.
Your Majesty,
Su Majestad,
I know something
Sé algo
that can prove that
que puede probar que
the late Prince Chengqing and Lord Wang
el difunto príncipe Chengqing y el señor Wang
not only had a lot of dealings,
no solo tuvo muchos tratos,
but were also
pero también lo eran
extremely close.
extremadamente cerca.
Is Jiuheng
es jiuheng
going against Lord Chengyuan
yendo en contra del Señor Chengyuan
in public?
¿en público?
They've held a grudge for years,
Llevan años guardando rencor.
and it could explode at any moment.
y podría explotar en cualquier momento.
Let's see what the Senior Grand Secretary intends to do.
Veamos qué piensa hacer el Gran Secretario Mayor.
On the 8th day of October in the 25th year of Jingning,
El 8 de octubre del año 25 de Jingning,
Vice Minister of War, Zhu Guoming,
Viceministro de Guerra, Zhu Guoming
celebrated his 60th birthday.
celebró su 60 cumpleaños.
The late Prince Chengqing and Lord Wang
El difunto príncipe Chengqing y el señor Wang
both attended the banquet.
Ambos asistieron al banquete.
The late Prince Chengqing brought two beautiful maids
El difunto príncipe Chengqing trajo consigo a dos hermosas doncellas.
and gifted them respectively to
y los obsequió respectivamente a
Zhu Guoming and Lord Wang.
Zhu Guoming y Lord Wang.
Chen Jiuheng,
Chen Jiu Heng,
do you have any evidence?
¿Tienes alguna prueba?
In October of the 26th year of Jingning,
En octubre del año 26 de Jingning,
news reached the capital
La noticia llegó a la capital.
that the late Prince Chengqing's rebellion
que la rebelión del difunto príncipe Chengqing
had failed, and he was
había fracasado y él estaba
slain by Marquis Changxing.
asesinado por el marqués Changxing.
Soon after, Zhu Guoming allegedly
Poco después, Zhu Guoming supuestamente
died of a sudden heart attack.
murió de un infarto repentino.
But what no one knew was
Pero lo que nadie sabía era
that in Lord Wang's mansion,
que en la mansión de Lord Wang,
a maid also died a sudden death.
Una criada también falleció repentinamente.
Zhu Guoming was proven to be
Se demostró que Zhu Guoming era
a traitor colluding with Prince Chengqing.
un traidor que conspiraba con el príncipe Chengqing.
His entire family was executed.
Toda su familia fue ejecutada.
Yet Lord Wang has lived in peace,
Sin embargo, Lord Wang ha vivido en paz,
and has even
y tiene incluso
been promoted repeatedly.
ha sido ascendido repetidamente.
Nonsense!
¡Disparates!
Your Majesty,
Su Majestad,
Chen Yanyun is framing me
Chen Yanyun me está tendiendo una trampa.
with baseless accusations,
con acusaciones infundadas,
because he knows
porque él sabe
I'm investigating
Estoy investigando
the case of Censor-in-Chief Gu Deyuan.
El caso del censor jefe Gu Deyuan.
As an imperial censor, Gu Deyuan
Como censor imperial, Gu Deyuan
covered up crimes for corrupt officials.
Encubrieron crímenes para funcionarios corruptos.
His niece is married to Chen Yanyun,
Su sobrina está casada con Chen Yanyun.
so he became Chen Yanyun's pawn.
Así que se convirtió en el peón de Chen Yanyun.
He accepted bribes many times
Aceptó sobornos muchas veces.
and sold official posts.
y vendió puestos oficiales.
I request a joint trial by the Three Judiciary Offices
Solicito un juicio conjunto por parte de las Tres Oficinas Judiciales.
to thoroughly investigate Chen Yanyun.
Investigar a fondo a Chen Yanyun.
But you two are both Grand Secretaries.
Pero ustedes dos son Grandes Secretarios.
[The Emperor Establishes Supreme Order]
[El Emperador Establece el Orden Supremo]
Mr. Fu, what is your opinion?
Señor Fu, ¿cuál es su opinión?
Your Majesty,
Su Majestad,
the nation has its laws.
La nación tiene sus leyes.
Even though the two of them are Grand Secretaries,
Aunque ambos son Grandes Secretarios,
it makes no difference.
No hay diferencia.
Since they have been impeached,
Dado que han sido sometidos a juicio político,
they should resign
deberían dimitir
and await punishment
y esperar castigo
until the Three Judiciary Offices
hasta que las Tres Oficinas Judiciales
conduct a full investigation.
llevar a cabo una investigación completa.
We shall do as Mr. Fu advises.
Haremos lo que aconseja el señor Fu.
[The Emperor Establishes Supreme Order]
[El Emperador Establece el Orden Supremo]
Mother.
Madre.
It's my fault for not raising you right.
Es culpa mía por no haberte educado bien.
Corruption and bribery
Corrupción y soborno
are things you should never touch.
Son cosas que nunca debes tocar.
I was wrong.
Me equivoqué.
I was so wrong.
Estaba muy equivocado.
Please take care of yourself
Por favor, cuídate.
while I'm gone.
mientras no estoy.
Leave.
Dejar.
I will take care
Yo me encargaré
of everything at the mansion.
de todo en la mansión.
Take him away.
Llévenselo.
Master.
Maestro.
Don't cry.
No llores.
Save your tears
Guarda tus lágrimas
when we get to the Chen Mansion.
cuando lleguemos a la Mansión Chen.
Right now,
Ahora mismo,
only Zhao
solo Zhao
can save Deyuan.
Puede salvar a Deyuan.
Third Master.
Tercer Maestro.
Let's go home.
Vámonos a casa.
Gu Deyuan was taken by the Court of Judicial Review.
Gu Deyuan fue llevado ante el Tribunal de Revisión Judicial.
The Gu family
La familia Gu
will definitely pester Jinzhao.
Sin duda molestaré a Jinzhao.
Yes. There's one more thing, Third Master.
Sí. Hay una cosa más, Tercer Maestro.
Madam went to
La señora fue a
Baoxiang Temple yesterday.
Templo de Baoxiang ayer.
I only found out about it
Recién me enteré de eso.
this morning.
esta mañana.
You were at court
Usted estaba en el tribunal
so I couldn't inform you.
Así que no pude informarte.
I understand. Let's go.
Lo entiendo. Vamos.
[Ancestral Virtues, Our Guiding Light]
[Las virtudes ancestrales, nuestra luz guía]
This happened many years ago.
Esto sucedió hace muchos años.
Now they're suddenly bringing it up again.
Ahora, de repente, vuelven a sacar el tema.
They said they'd investigate thoroughly
Dijeron que investigarían a fondo.
and locked your second uncle up
y encerró a tu segundo tío
in the Court of Judicial Review.
en el Tribunal de Revisión Judicial.
They won't even let us visit him.
Ni siquiera nos dejan visitarlo.
Zhao,
Zhao,
talk to your husband
Habla con tu marido
and ask him to save your second uncle.
y pídele que salve a tu segundo tío.
I'm afraid that won't be easy.
Me temo que no será fácil.
What are you talking about?
¿De qué estás hablando?
Your husband is the Grand Secretary.
Su esposo es el Gran Secretario.
Saving someone's life
Salvar la vida de alguien
is just a matter of a word from him.
Es cuestión de una sola palabra por su parte.
Zhao,
Zhao,
we are family.
Somos familia.
If something happens
Si algo sucede
to your second uncle,
a tu segundo tío,
it won't look good
no se verá bien
for you and your husband.
Para ti y tu esposo.
It's not that I don't want to help,
No es que no quiera ayudar,
but the crime
pero el crimen
Second Uncle committed
El segundo tío se comprometió
is just far too serious.
es demasiado serio.
And the evidence is concrete.
Y las pruebas son concretas.
How is the evidence concrete?
¿Cómo se puede afirmar que las pruebas son concretas?
You are a member of the Gu family.
Eres miembro de la familia Gu.
How can you say that?
¿Cómo puedes decir eso?
Second Madam.
Segunda señora.
My Lady
Mi Señora
caught a cold last night
Anoche me resfrié.
and isn't feeling well right now.
y no se encuentra bien en este momento.
How about
¿Qué tal si...?
you come back another day?
¿Volverás otro día?
Zhao!
¡Zhao!
For the sake of my pregnancy,
Por el bien de mi embarazo,
please save my father.
Por favor, salven a mi padre.
I beg you, Zhao.
Te lo ruego, Zhao.
Miss Lan,
Señorita Lan,
please stop pulling at my lady.
Por favor, deja de tirar de mi mujer.
Zhao,
Zhao,
I really
Realmente lo siento
have no other way.
No tengo otra opción.
The entire Yao family
Toda la familia Yao
is heartless.
es despiadado.
After seeing what happened to my father,
Después de ver lo que le pasó a mi padre,
they can't wait to cut ties with me.
Están deseando romper lazos conmigo.
Zhao.
Zhao.
Now I finally realize
Ahora por fin me doy cuenta
that we are family.
que somos familia.
I was wrong before.
Me equivoqué antes.
Zhao.
Zhao.
Lian!
¡Su!
-Lian.
-Lian.
Fetch a physician!
¡Llama a un médico!
-No.
-Lián. -No.
Fetch a female physician instead.
Busque una médica en su lugar.
Don't let anyone know.
No dejes que nadie se entere.
Lian.
Lian.
Yes.
Sí.
Didn't we agree
¿No estuvimos de acuerdo?
to prepare for the wedding at home?
¿Prepararse para la boda en casa?
Why did you suddenly move into the academy?
¿Por qué te mudaste repentinamente a la academia?
Since you moved out,
Desde que te mudaste,
you haven't come back to pay your respects.
No has vuelto para presentar tus respetos.
That is one thing.
Esa es una cosa.
And I heard
Y escuché
that even when you need clothes or books,
que incluso cuando necesitas ropa o libros,
you only send your servants
Solo envías a tus sirvientes
to sneak in, collect your things, and leave.
para colarte, recoger tus cosas y marcharte.
Those who know the situation
Quienes conocen la situación
will say you're busy with work.
dirás que estás ocupado con el trabajo.
Those who don't
Los que no lo hacen
might think the family mistreated you.
Puede que pienses que tu familia te maltrató.
I know
Sé
you have a lot on your mind,
Tienes muchas cosas en la cabeza,
but I don't care
pero no me importa
what exactly you're thinking.
¿Qué es exactamente lo que estás pensando?
Since your surname is Chen,
Dado que su apellido es Chen,
in everything you do,
en todo lo que hagas,
you can't just
no puedes simplemente
think about yourself.
Piensa en ti mismo.
You must also consider this family.
También debes tener en cuenta a esta familia.
Grandmother,
Abuela,
you misunderstood.
Lo has entendido mal.
-Old Madam. -I...
-Vieja señora. -Yo...
Old Madam,
Vieja señora,
the Gu family is making a scene
La familia Gu está armando un escándalo.
at Third Madam's courtyard.
en el patio de la Tercera Señora.
For some reason,
Por alguna razón,
they even summoned a female physician.
Incluso llamaron a una médica.
Don't tell me something went wrong there?
¿No me digas que algo salió mal ahí?
Grandmother, I'll go take a look.
Abuela, voy a echar un vistazo.
It's karma.
Es karma.
It's all my karma catching up to me.
Es mi karma el que me está alcanzando.
It's good that she is fine.
Me alegro de que esté bien.
Let her get some proper rest now.
Que descanse bien ahora.
Ms. Zhao,
Sra. Zhao,
please take good care of her.
Por favor, cuídala bien.
I don't feel well.
No me siento bien.
I'm going out for some fresh air.
Voy a salir a tomar un poco de aire fresco.
Yes, My Lady.
Sí, mi señora.
Please take care of yourself.
Por favor, cuídate.
Why are you here?
¿Por qué estás aquí?
Aren't you sick?
¿No estás enfermo?
Why are you still outside?
¿Por qué sigues afuera?
Let go of me!
¡Suéltame!
-You're already in this state, -Let go of me!
-Ya estás en este estado, -¡Suéltame!
yet you still care about such things?
¿Y aún te importan esas cosas?
Let go of me!
¡Suéltame!
Why must you
¿Por qué debes hacerlo?
keep pushing me away?
¿Sigues alejándome?
Let go of me!
¡Suéltame!
Have you forgotten
¿Lo has olvidado?
everything you ever said to me?
¿Todo lo que me has dicho alguna vez?
Let go of me!
¡Suéltame!
Third Master.
Tercer Maestro.
Third Uncle.
Tercer tío.
I...
I...
You can't do this.
No puedes hacer esto.
My grandmother
Mi abuela
and second aunt are both inside.
y la segunda tía están ambas adentro.
Let go.
Déjalo ir.
Let go!
¡Déjalo ir!
Get lost!
¡Piérdase!
About what happened today,
Sobre lo que sucedió hoy,
don't breathe a word of it to anyone!
¡No le digas ni una palabra a nadie!
Don't let me see you again!
¡No quiero volver a verte!
Why?
¿Por qué?
Why should you?
¿Por qué deberías hacerlo?
Do you think
¿Crees que...?
just because you are the Grand Secretary,
solo porque usted es el Gran Secretario,
you can decide life and death
Tú puedes decidir sobre la vida y la muerte.
and do whatever you want?
¿Y hacer lo que quieras?
Do you know
Sabes
that I was the one she liked first?
¿Que yo fui el primero que le gustó?
It was you
Fuiste tú
who meddled in
quien se entrometió en
and took her away from me.
y me la arrebató.
If it weren't for you,
Si no fuera por ti,
we would've been together long ago!
¡Habríamos estado juntos hace mucho tiempo!
[A Splendid Match]
[Un partido espléndido]